Guide to the Robert E. Butts Papers, 1908-1997 ASP.2000.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Robert E. Butts Papers
1908-1997
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Butts, Robert E.
ASP.2000.01
15 Linear Feet
Robert Earl Butts was a philosopher of science whose research interests included the work of Leibniz, Newton, Galileo, Whewell, and Kant. He spent most of his career as a faculty member at the University of Western Ontario and was active in professional organizations and publications in the history and philosophy of science. The papers consist of biographical materials, including educational documents, early writings and schoolwork, photographs, correspondence, and memorabilia; and professional materials, including correspondence, research and lecture notes, records of publications and professional organizations, and unpublished drafts.
Biography
Robert Earl Butts was born in Lancaster, Pennsylvania, in 1928 and died in 1997 in London, Ontario, Canada. After attending Manheim Township High School from 1943-1947, he earned his A.B. and A.M. in philosophy from Syracuse University in 1951 and 1952, respectively, and his PhD from the University of Pennsylvania in 1957. He joined the philosophy department at the University of Western Ontario in 1963, where he would remain until his death. He also lectured at a number of prestigious institutions through fellowships and visiting appointments, including the University of Pittsburgh's Center for Philosophy of Science.
Butts was an active author and researcher in the field of history and philosophy of science and was deeply involved in his professional community, maintaining close personal and professional relationships with many prominent philosophers of his time. He edited and authored monographs on Whewell, Newton, Galileo, and Kant, as well as contributing prolifically to professional journals, anthologies, and encyclopedias. He served as editor-in-chief of Philosophy of Science from 1980-1990, and was managing editor of the University of Western Ontario Series in Philosophy of Science from 1979 until his death. He was chairman of the Canadian National Committee of the International Union of History and Philosophy of Science from 1978 to 1991, and was an active member of many other professional organizations.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following four series:
Series I. Biographical Materials, 1908-1997
Series II. Professional Materials, 1951-1997
Series III. Multimedia, 1972-1997
Series IV. Oversized Materials, 1947-1994
Scope and Content Notes
The Robert Earl Butts Papers document Butts' life and work as an academic in the field of scientific philosophy during the latter half of the twentieth century. Biographical materials consist of documents concerning Butts' personal life as a son, brother, husband, father, and friend. There is particular emphasis on his early life in Pennsylvania and his education at Manheim Township High School, with a less significant amount of memorabilia relating to his later life.
The larger body of professional papers contains material concerning Butts' active involvement in his community of academic peers. He played a leadership role in a number of national and international professional organizations and conferences, as well as writing and editing numerous publications and serving as a mentor to many of his peers and students. His papers document these and other functions that he carried out as a faculty member and philosopher.
The collection consists primarily of paper documents housed in legal-sized document boxes. Box 7 contains photographs, mostly family portraits from Butts' early life. Box 28 contains a variety of alternative media, mainly cassette tapes and floppy disks, much of the content of which is unknown. Box 29 contains oversized documents such as diplomas and certificates. Materials are arranged either chronologically or alphabetically where possible. Untitled, undated, or miscellaneous materials are generally found at the end of the folder or file group. Additional scope and content notes are provided at the series and subseries level.
Previous Citation
Robert Earl Butts Papers, 1908-1997, ASP.2000.01, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Acquisition Information
Gift of Valentine Watson Rodgers in May 2000.
Related Material
Nicholas Rescher Papers, 1957-2005, ASP.2009.01, Archives of Scientific Philosophy, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Access Restrictions
Portions of the collection (approximately 2 linear feet) that contain personally identifiable, private, confidential, or sensitive information have been physically removed and are closed indefinitely to public access. This includes private correspondence between Butts and his family as well as legal and medical records and material containing confidential information about students and colleagues.
Science -- Philosophy -- Congresses; Philosophy, Canadian -- 20th century; Philosophers -- Canada; College teachers -- Canada; Universities and colleges -- Faculty -- Canada; Lancaster (Pa.); Manheim (Lancaster County, Pa.: Township); Correspondence; Photographs; University of Western Ontario series in philosophy of science; Slides (Photographs); Science -- Methodology -- History; Science -- Methodology -- Philosophy; Science -- Philosophy; International Congress of Logic, Methodology, and Philosophy of Science; Pisa Conference on the History and Philosophy of Science (1978); International Union of the History and Philosophy of Science. Division of Logic, Methodology and Philosophy of Science; International Union of the History and Philosophy of Science. Division of History of Science; International Union of the History and Philosophy of Science; Canadian Philosophical Association; University of Pittsburgh. Center for Philosophy of Science; Universität Konstanz; University of Western Ontario; Mittelstrass, Jürgen; Butts, Robert E.
- Biographical Materials, 1908-1997; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains material related to Butts' upbringing, his personal life, and his relationships and activities outside of the professional community. Many of the documents are from the period of approximately 1943 to 1952, which encompasses Butts' high school and undergraduate education. During this time, he was active in school and community activities such as Key Club, theater, student government, and the high school newspaper. From 1944-1945, Butts corresponded with his brother, who was stationed on the European front of World War II. He was also an avid writer in his youth; a number of folders and notebooks in this series are dedicated to poetry and prose that Butts wrote during his high school and college years.
  The material from Butts' later life in this series is concentrated on memorabilia such as invitations and newspaper clippings pertaining both to events in Butts' own life and current events and topics that were of interest to him. There is also a large group of brochures and guides from his travels in Europe during the 1980s and 1990s.
  - Educational Documents, 1941-1952; 1.
    This subseries consists of report cards and other administrative materials relating to Butts' education at the various institutions described above. Some material, mainly consisting of diplomas and other educational certificates, has been removed due to size restrictions and placed in Box 29.
    - Report Cards, 1941-1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Educational Documents from Syracuse, 1947-1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Schoolwork and Early Writings, 1945-1957; 2.
    This subseries documents Butts' development as a writer and scholar from high school through his years as a graduate student at Penn and Syracuse. It includes formal assignments as well as personal reflections and creative projects. The material in this series is unpublished and predates Butts' formal work as an academic researcher.
    - Notes and Assignments (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Pressed Flower Collection, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 12th Grade English Notebook, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Poetry and Prose from High School and College, 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Graduate School Papers, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Poetry and Prose, 1947-1951 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Doctoral Dissertation, Part 1: "Husserl's Criticism of Hume's Theory of Knowledge," University of Pennsylvania, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Doctoral Dissertation, Part 2: "Husserl's Criticism of Hume's Theory of Knowledge," University of Pennsylvania, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Master Thesis "Man in a World: The Ethics of Existentialism," Syracuse University, May 1952 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Memorabilia, 1908-1997; 3.
    The items in this subseries document the broad variety of Butt's private activities and interests. Over the course of his life, he collected newspaper clippings documenting achievements and milestones for himself and his family, as well as some current events and general topics of interest; programs and brochures from various events he participated in or attended; and maps, brochures, and souvenirs from his travels, especially those in Europe during the 1970s, 80s, and 90s. This subseries also includes items such as report cards and yearbooks that belonged to Butts' father and older brother.
    - Artwork by Butts and Others (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - George Butts, Sr. School Materials, 1908-1923 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - George Butts, Sr. Lancaster High Yearbook (2 Copies), 1918 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - George Butts, Jr. School Projects (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - George Butts, Jr. School Notes (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Clippings on George Butts, Jr. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Clippings on George Butts, Sr., 1937 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Clippings on Death of Elizabeth A. Saylor Butts, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - High School Yearbook, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - High School Newspapers, 1945-1947 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - High School Certificates and Awards, 1943-1947 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - High School Invitations and Programs, 1944-1947 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - High School Current Events (Clippings) (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - High School Sports (Clippings) (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - High School Theater (Clippings) (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - High School Key Club (Clippings) (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - High School Graduation (Clippings), 1947 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Army Publications from World War II (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Official Army Photographs from World War II (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - World War II Ration Books (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Syracuse University, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - University of Pennsylvania, 1952-1957 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Phi Sigma Tau National Honor Society for Philosophy, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - High School Reunion (Clipping) (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Birth and Wedding Announcements and Invitations (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Creationism (Clippings) (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - George Rockwell Visits Bucknell (Clippings), 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Issues of Western News, 1990-1996 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Lancaster Intelligencer-Journal, Grandmother's 100th Birthday, December 5, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Personal Forecast and Life Development Chart Prepared by Irene Hughes of Astral Sciences International, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Notes Found in Books from Butts' Personal Library (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Event Programs, 1972-1994 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Souvenirs (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Travel - Association Terre de Rhedae (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Guidebooks (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Maps and Brochures (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Travel Receipts and Expense Reports, 1973-1996 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Executive Travel London Ltd. (Correspondence and Paperwork), 1982-1985 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Album of Travel Brochures and Postcards (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Material Related to Butts' Death, 1997; 4.
    This subseries consists mostly of correspondence that occurred between his widow and grieving family, friends, and colleagues after Butt's sudden death in 1997. Also included are some funeral plans and copies of obituaries from various publications.
    - Letters from Valentine Watson Rodgers to Friends, Family, and Colleagues, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Obituaries and Funeral Plans, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Condolences (Notes and Cards), 1997 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Condolences (Letters and Emails), 1997 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Personal Correspondence, 5.
    The correspondence in this subseries is mostly of a general nature, consisting of notes, letters, and cards that Butts exchanged with various family members and friends over the course of his life. Of particular note are the 1944-1945 letters from his older brother, who was stationed in Europe during World War II. Due to their private and/or sensitive nature, a large number of documents from this subseries are included in the restricted material described at the beginning of this finding aid.
    - Childhood Correspondence, 1935-1936 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence with George Butts, Jr. During WWII, 1944-1945 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - General Correspondence with Friends and Family, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - High School Alumni Association, 1982-1995 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Vendors and Organizations, 1976-1985 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Postcards and Greeting Cards, 1942, 1983-1994 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Christmas Cards (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Birthday Cards (Mostly 60th), 1988 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Photographs, 6.
    Most of the photographs in this subseries are family photographs from Butts' youth, including both studio portraits and candids, and group photos of student organizations from his time at Manheim Township High School. Images that hung framed in his office, many of them of Kant, comprise another significant portion of this subseries. Of particular note is the baby book that Butts' parents filled out for him shortly after his birth in 1928; an infant's knit garment in excellent condition was found tucked into the back cover and remains in the file.
    - Portrait of Butts, Brother George, and Mother Elizabeth (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - George Butts, Sr. and Brother John Butts (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - George Butts, Sr. Holding George Butts, Jr. (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Family Vacation (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Class Photo, possibly of George Butts, Sr. (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Baby Photo of "George," possibly George Butts, Jr. (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Unidentified Baby Photos (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Portraits of Butts and Brother George as Children (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - High School (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - High School Theater (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - High School Sports (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Signed Portraits of Performers (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Framed Photo: "O. Baumberger: Zwingli - Schweiz. Komission fur gute religiose Bilder" (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Family Photos (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Photos of Kant (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous Family Photos (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Travel Photos (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Polaroids and Slides of Silversmith Work (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Album of Postcards and Photos (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Baby Book (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Art Slides (Box 7, Folder 21)
- Professional Materials, 1951-1997; II.
  This series contains documents pertaining to Butts' life and work as a researcher, author, and active member of his professional community. The papers in this series document Butt's longtime involvement in a variety of professional activities and the respect and camaraderie he enjoyed among his academic peers. The largest portion of this series is dedicated to unpublished drafts of works authored by both Butts and his peers; he was frequently consulted as both an official referee and an informal colleague.
  Researchers will notice the same names and subjects appearing in multiple locations throughout the series; this is due to the intimate nature of the field of scientific philosophy, in which the same actors appear as journal contributors, book editors, grant applicants, committee members, and close personal friends at various points in Butt's life.
  - Research, Writing, and Publication, 1951-1996; 1.
    Butts was active as both an author and editor of publications in the field of scientific philosophy. These functions are also closely related to his role as a researcher and an academic. This subseries consists of a broad variety of materials that document these interrelated professional functions. Of particular note is the extensive correspondence with authors and editors that Butts conducted in his capacity as editor of the Western Ontario Series in Philosophy of Science, published by Reidel and later Kluwer Academic Publishers from 1973-1996, which is arranged chronologically in Section 1 of the subseries. This is distinct from the correspondence in Section 3, which relates to individual works that Butts personally wrote or edited. Also significant is the large number of unpublished drafts of Butts' academic work found in Section 2.
    - Publications Edited by Butts, 1973-1996; 1.
      This section contains two groups of material: correspondence and administrative records related to the publications that Butts oversaw, and reviews of those publications. The latter are listed according to the author of the work being reviewed.
      - Western Ontario Series Contract (Reidel), 1973 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Western Ontario Series Publishing Agreements (Kluwer and Reidel), 1973-1994 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - Reidel Royalty Statements, 1973-1988 (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Kluwer Royalty Statements, 1990-1992 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Western Ontario Series Financial Records, 1973-1989 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Western Ontario Series General Correspondence, 1974-1994 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Reidel Correspondence, 1974-1980 (Box 8, Folder 7-9)
      - Reidel Correspondence, 1982-1984 (Box 8, Folder 10-12)
      - Reidel Correspondence, 1985-1988 (Box 9, Folder 1-4)
      - Kluwer Correspondence, 1987-1993 (Box 9, Folder 5-11)
      - Kluwer Correspondence, 1994 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Kluwer Correspondence, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Philosophy of Science Weekly Reports, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Philosophy of Science General Correspondence, 1978-1986 (Box 10, Folder 4)
      - Review of William Shea's "Basic Issues in the Philosophy of Science", 1976 (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - Review of Fred Wilson's "Empiricism and Darwin's Science", 1991 (Box 10, Folder 6)
      - Review of Henry B. Hollinger and Michael J. Zenzen's "The Nature of Irreversibility", 1985 (Box 10, Folder 7)
      - Review of Michael Ruse's "Is Science Sexist?" (Box 10, Folder 8)
      - Review of Nicholas Rescher's "Leibniz's Metaphysics of Nature", 1981 (Box 10, Folder 9)
      - Review of I.B. NacNeill and G.J. Umphrey's "Stochastic Hydrology", 1987 (Box 10, Folder 10)
      - Review of C.A. Hooker, ed., Physical Theory as Logico-Operational Structure, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 11)
      - Review of Larry Laudan's "Science and Hypothesis", 1981 (Box 10, Folder 12)
      - Review of Graham Oddie's "Likeness to Truth", 1986 (Box 10, Folder 13)
      - Review of James Robert Brown and Jurgen Mittelstrass, eds., An Intimate Relation, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 14)
      - Review of James Robert Brown's "Scientific Rationality: The Sociological Turn", 1984 (Box 10, Folder 15)
      - Reviews of Jürgen Mittelstrass, ed., Enzyklopadie Philosophie und Wissenschaftstheorie (Box 10, Folder 16)
      - Review of Jürgen Mittelstrass' "Zwei Erfahrungsbegriffe" (Box 10, Folder 17)
      - Review Clippings from Reidel (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Unpublished Drafts by Butts, 1965-1996; 2.
      - "The Appraisal of Scientific Theories: A New Use of the Internal/External Distinction" (Abstract) (Box 10, Folder 19)
      - "Comment on L. Jonathan Cohen, 'Some Historical Remarks on the Baconian Conception of Probability'," Author's Proof (Box 10, Folder 19a)
      - "Experience and Experiment as Regulative Principles in Methodology", 1973 (Box 10, Folder 20)
      - "The Grammar of Reason" (Box 10, Folder 21)
      - "The Grammar of Reason: Hamann's Challenge to Kant", 1985 (Box 10, Folder 22)
      - "Induction as Unification: Kant, Whewell, and Recent Developments", May 1992 (Box 10, Folder 23)
      - "Kant and the Problem of Locating Souls", November 1985 (Box 10, Folder 24)
      - "Kant on Revolutionary Changes in the Methods of the Sciences", April 1988 (Box 10, Folder 25)
      - "Kant's Alleged Failure to Construct the Concepts of Fundamental Forces", May 1985 (Box 10, Folder 26)
      - "Kant's Dialectic and the Logic of Illusion", May 1995 (Box 10, Folder 27)
      - "Kant's Philosophy of Science: The Transition from Metaphysics to Science", 1984 (Box 10, Folder 28)
      - "Kant's Proof of the Objective Reality of the Categories" (Box 10, Folder 29)
      - "Kant's Realization of 'Galileo's Program'", June 1974 (Box 10, Folder 30)
      - "Kant's Theory of Musical Sound: An Early Exercise in Cognitive Science" (Box 10, Folder 31)
      - "Herschel, John Frederick William" (Box 10, Folder 32)
      - "Leibniz on Empirical Methodology", 1983 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - "Leibniz on Choosing Between Rival Scientific Hypotheses", September 1990 (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - "Leibniz on the Side of Angels", Spring 1982 (Box 11, Folder 3)
      - "Metaphysical Mirages and Kant's Logic of Illusion", March 1994 (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - "Metaphysics, Methodology, and the Pragmatic Unity of the Science", June 1990 (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - "The Methodological Structure of Kant's Metaphysics of Science", 1984 (Box 11, Folder 6)
      - "Methodological Structure of Metaphysics of Science" (Box 11, Folder 7)
      - "'Le Mouvement...n'est pas une chose entierement reele': Leibniz, Discours de Metaphysique" (Box 11, Folder 8)
      - "Necessary Truth in Whewell's Theory of Science", July 1965 (Box 11, Folder 9)
      - "Orthodoxy in Philosophy of Science, 1930-1962: How Did It Come About?", January 1987 (Box 11, Folder 10)
      - "Philosophers as Professional Relativists" (Box 11, Folder 11)
      - "Philosophy of Science in the Nineteenth Century" (Box 11, Folder 12)
      - "Pragmatism in Theories of Induction in the Victorian Era: Herschel, Whewell, Mach, and Mill", January 1984 (Box 11, Folder 13)
      - "Proceeding Case by Case: Saving the Methodological Appearances", March-April 1984 (Box 11, Folder 14)
      - "Proceeding Case by Case: Saving the Methodological Appearances" (Appendix) (Box 11, Folder 15)
      - "'A Purely Scientific Temper': Victorian Expressions of the Ideal of an Autonomous Science", April 5, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 16)
      - "The Reception of German Scientific Philosophy in North America: 1930-1962", March 1996 (Box 11, Folder 17)
      - "The Role of Arational Factors in Interpretive History: The Case of Kant and ESP", January 1983 (Box 11, Folder 18)
      - "Rules, Examples, and Constructions: Kant's Theory of Mathematics" (2 Proofs) (Box 11, Folder 19)
      - "Science and the Humanities: A Historical and Analytical Comparison", November 1991-December 1992 (Box 11, Folder 20)
      - "Spencer, Herbert" (Box 11, Folder 21)
      - "Testability" (Box 11, Folder 22)
      - "Two Stories About Evil: Christianity and the Creation of Witches", 1992 (Box 11, Folder 23)
      - Untitled, Coauthored by James R. Brown (Box 11, Folder 24)
      - William Whewell's Theory of Scientific Method (Proposal and Outline) (Box 11, Folder 25)
      - "Whewell on Newton's Rules of Philosophizing", Winter 1965 (Box 11, Folder 26)
      - "Whewell's Inductive Tables" (2 Copies) (Box 11, Folder 27)
      - "Whewell, William" (Box 11, Folder 28)
    - Works Authored and Edited by Butts: Correspondence and Administrative Documents, 1970-1986; 3.